Guide to the Dick Thornburgh Papers, 1932- AIS.1998.30.04
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Dick Thornburgh Papers, Series IV. Politics
1960s-1970s
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Thornburgh, Dick
AIS.1998.30.04
4.38 Linear Feet
Dick Thornburgh's participation in rebuilding the Republican Party became pronounced after the 1964 presidential election, resulting in his article "The Republican Party in the City of Pittsburgh: A Tentative Analysis and Some Recommendations," available here online. Subsequently, Thornburgh was appointed to the GOP Platform Committee, became increasingly involved in political organizations, wrote other articles, and participated in many campaigns at the local and state levels. At the national level, Thornburgh was active with the John Lindsay campaigns for Congress and Mayor of New York, and Nelson Rockefeller's campaign for the presidential nomination in 1968. These varying campaign files provide an excellent look at politics of the time, particularly in Allegheny County. Those interested in campaigns of this period should also refer to "Campaign for U.S. Congress, 1966." The files here are in five sections: GOP Committees and Activities; Research and Notes on Politics; Campaigns; John Lindsay Campaigns; and Rockefeller for President. Digital reproductions of portions of the collection are available online.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Dick Thornburgh, February 27, 1998
Previous Citation
Dick Thornburgh Papers, 1932-, AIS.1998.30, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Personal papers; Pittsburgh (Pa.) -- Politics and government; Government; Pennsylvania -- Politics and government -- 1951-; Politics; Political corruption -- United States; Political corruption -- Pennsylvania; Urban renewal -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Kirkpatrick & Lockhart; Thornburgh, Dick
- Politics, 1960s-1970s; IV.
  Scope and Contents note
  While interested in politics generally, it was after the 1964 presidential election when Lyndon Johnson (D) defeated Barry Goldwater (R) that Thornburgh's participation in rebuilding the Republican Party became pronounced. In his book, Where the Evidence Leads, Thornburgh writes of a dinner party where his hostess responded to his political diatribe by suggesting that he "...do something about it." He states that "over the next six weeks, I undertook a crash course in Practical Politics 101, [and by] studying census tracts and election results, I constructed a fairly reliable political profile of Pittsburgh and Allegheny County, the extent of my immediate horizon" (Evidence, p. 22). These files are, in many ways, the documentary evidence of Thornburgh's research which resulted most notably in his article "The Republican Party in the City of Pittsburgh: A Tentative Analysis and Some Recommendations" which was circulated privately among local and state party leaders and is available here online.
  Subsequently Thornburgh was appointed to the GOP Platform Committee, became increasingly involved in political organizations, wrote other articles, and participated in many campaigns at the local and state levels. At the national level, Thornburgh was active with the John Lindsay campaigns for Congress and Mayor of New York, and Nelson Rockefeller's team recruited Thornburgh as their Western Pennsylvania chairman in his campaign for the Republican presidential nomination in 1968. These varying campaign files provide an excellent look at politics of the time, particularly in Allegheny County.
  Those interested in campaigns should also refer to the section entitled "Campaign for U.S. Congress, 1966." One of the results of all Thornburgh's research was this determined campaign for Congress that is well documented in the archive. His loss was not surprising, running against a strong Democrat incumbent, but the experience served well to stimulate him into increasing political activity, particularly the Lindsay and Rockefeller campaigns, more national in import. The Campaign for U.S. Congress falls in the same time frame as these "Politics" files, but the campaign files are in such quantity and depth that they have been arranged separately.
  Researchers also should note the unavoidable overlaps in time and even some content with files in "Early Legal Career," "Pittsburgh Civic Activity," "Campaign for U.S. Congress," " Constitutional Convention," and "U.S. Attorney." For example, correspondence in one section may well pertain to issues or situations in another area and political activity is represented in the "Campaign for U.S. Congress" as well as more generally here. Also valuable, Ginny Thornburgh put together scrapbooks of Thornburgh's clippings that effectively document his increasingly public career and activities during these years. This valuable resource has been reformatted and is available in the archives (Section 21).
  The "Politics" files are organized into five sections: "GOP Committees and Activities"; "Research and Notes on Politics"; "Campaigns"; "John Lindsay Campaigns"; and "Rockefeller for President."
  - GOP Committees and Activities, 1.
    The files here document the Republican committees and activities in which Thornburgh was involved in efforts to revitalize the party locally. The materials are arranged chronologically and consist of correspondence, annotated notes, minutes, memoranda, and reports. Included are two articles Thornburgh wrote about the Republican Party in Pittsburgh, both of which are available here online and indicative of Thornburgh's energetic participation in the political scene at the time.
    - Political Correspondence, 1964-1965 (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - Republican Platform Committee, Correspondence and Notes, 1965 (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - Republican Research and Planning Corporation, Notes and Research, 1965 (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - Proposed Allegheny County Republican Forum: draft memorandum by Dick Thornburgh and John Heinz, Co-chairmen of Committee, December, 1965 (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - "The Republican Party in the City of Pittsburgh: A Tentative Analysis and Some Recommendations," by Richard L. Thornburgh, 1965 (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - Republicans for Progress, 1965-1967 (Box 17, Folder 13)
    - Ripon Society, 1965-1974 (Box 17, Folder 14)
    - Political Correspondence, 1966 (Box 17, Folder 15)
    - Allegheny Republican Council By-Laws, Correspondence, and Minutes, 1966-1968 (Box 17, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence, 1967 (Box 17, Folder 17)
    - Allegheny County Republican Party Rules Committee, 1967 (Box 17, Folder 18)
    - Allegheny County Republican Research and Issues Committee: Memorandum, Correspondence, Notes, and Reports, 1967 (Box 17, Folder 19)
    - Republican Executive Committee of Allegheny County, 1967-1968 (Box 17, Folder 20)
    - 14th Ward Republican Committee, 1967-1971 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Political Correspondence, 1968 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Pennsylvania Council of Republican Women, 1968 (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - 1968 Republican Convention, Programs, Schedules, and Memorabilia, July-August, 1968 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Research and Notes on Politics, 2.
    The files here successfully represent the political scene in Pittsburgh at the time, including several local campaigns and the state of Pittsburgh's finances and mayoral politics. Files are arranged chronologically and consist of annotated notes, newspaper clippings, reports, and news releases about Pittsburgh politics and issues. The news releases are available here online.
    - Notes and research on statistical material regarding politics, 1960-1965 (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - Research on the Republican Party, 1964-1966 (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - Biographical information, notes, and clippings on Honorable Michael J. Musmanno, 1964 (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - Thornburgh's research and notes on politics, 1965 (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - "The State of Allegheny: The Republican Party in Pittsburgh and Allegheny County from 1930-1961," by H. Sheldon Parker, 1965 (Box 18, Folder 9)
    - Republican Party in Pittsburgh and Allegheny County, reports and notes, 1965-1977 (Box 18, Folder 10)
    - Research on election reform matters, 1967-1974 (Box 18, Folder 11)
    - Mayor Joseph Barr regarding Pittsburgh's financial crisis, 1968 (Box 18, Folder 12)
    - News Releases regarding politics in Pittsburgh, January, 1969 (Box 18, Folder 13)
      - Thornburgh hits Barr tax plan as "last ditch and half-hearted", April 24, 1968; 1.
      - Thornburgh charged that provisions of the City's 1969 budget calling for a pay raise for Mayor Joseph M. Barr are "unauthorized by law an therefore illegal.", December 30, 1968; 2.
      - Thornburgh hits Barr for "unqualified" magistrate appointment, 1968; 3.
      - Thornburgh suggested that it was "unwise" of Pittsburgh Public Safety Director Craig to accept position of general counsel for ACTION-Housing, Inc., area's largest non-profit corporation concerned with housing matters, January-February, 1969; 4.
      - Bar Official raps District Attorney on legal aid to poor, undated; 5.
      - Average citizen in Pittsburgh need somewhere to go with complaints (Ombudsman), undated; 6.
    - Research and correspondence regarding elections and polls in Pennsylvania, 1961-1972 (Box 18, Folder 14)
    - Information regarding Mayor Zoran Popovich, 1972 (Box 18, Folder 15)
    - Observations on the Pennsylvania political scene, 1972 and 1974 (Box 18, Folder 16)
  - Campaigns, 3.
    The breadth and depth of Thornburgh's political participation is well documented in these numerous and various campaigns during the sixties and seventies. Many are local (Cohill for Judge, Bob Friend for Comptroller, Gary for Alderman, for example), some statewide (Scranton for Governor, Judge Hannum, State Senator Clark, and McGregor for State Senator, for example) and others national (Heinz for Senator, Eisenhower-Nixon, for example). These files consist of correspondence, annotated notes, and campaign material. There is also material about a potential Thornburgh Pittsburgh mayoral candidacy (1972).
    - Pittsburgh and Allegheny County
      - Pittsburgh and Allegheny County political scene, 1965 (Box 18, Folder 17)
      - Judge Maurice Cohill campaign management, September-November, 1965 (Box 18, Folder 18)
      - Judge Cohill Campaign Correspondence, July, 1965-January, 1966 (Box 18, Folder 19)
      - Bob Friend: Candidacy for Comptroller, Allegheny County, 1967 (Box 18, Folder 20)
      - Algia Gary: Republican Candidate for Alderman, 13th Ward of Pittsburgh, 1967 (Box 18, Folder 21)
      - Republican Party of Allegheny County, Richard Thornburgh, City Coordinator, Primary, March, 1967 (Box 19, Folder 1)
      - Pittsburgh and Allegheny County Political Scene, 1967-1968 (Box 19, Folder 2)
      - Political Party Campaign Mailings, 1968 (Box 19, Folder 3)
      - Candidate Campaign Mailings, 1968 (Box 19, Folder 4)
      - Pittsburgh and Allegheny County political scene, 1969 (Box 19, Folder 5)
      - Campaign materials, 1969 (Box 19, Folder 6)
      - Pittsburgh and Allegheny County political scene, 1970 (Box 19, Folder 7)
      - Pittsburgh and Allegheny County political scene, Primary, 1971 (Box 19, Folder 8)
      - Pittsburgh and Allegheny County political scene, 1971 (Box 19, Folder 9)
      - Catarinella for Congress (14th Ward, Pittsburgh), ca. 1971 (Box 19, Folder 10)
      - Pittsburgh and Allegheny County political scene, 1972 (Box 19, Folder 11)
      - Information generated in response to Thornburgh's potential Pittsburgh Mayoral candidacy, 1972 (Box 19, Folder 12)
      - Pittsburgh and Allegheny County political scene, 1973 (Box 19, Folder 13)
    - Pennsylvania
      - Citizens for Scranton-VanZandt, correspondence and notes, June-November, 1962 (Box 19, Folder 14)
      - Citizens for Scranton-VanZandt, county citizens checklists, 1962 (Box 19, Folder 15)
      - Senator Jack E. McGregor, correspondence, 1965 (Box 19, Folder 16)
      - Judge John B. Hannum, Superior Court of Pennsylvania Campaign, 1968 (Box 19, Folder 17)
      - U.S. Senate Campaign in Pennsylvania, 1968 (Box 19, Folder 18)
      - Joseph S. Clark: Campaign for State Senator in Pennsylvania, campaign mailings, 1968 (Box 19, Folder 19)
      - Richard Schweiker: U.S. Senate Campaign in Pennsylvania, campaign mailings, 1968 (Box 19, Folder 20)
      - Jim McGregor: Campaign for State Senator, 1970 (Box 19, Folder 21)
      - Jack McGregor: Campaign for PA Governor, 1970 (Box 19, Folder 22)
      - John Heinz, U.S. Senate Campaign in Pennsylvania, correspondence, notes, and news releases, 1976 (Box 19, Folder 23)
    - National
      - Eisenhower and Nixon, Presidential Campaign, 1956 (Box 19, Folder 24)
      - Johnson and Goldwater, Presidential Campaign, 1964 (Box 19, Folder 25)
      - Election '64: A Ripon Society Report, 1965 (Box 19, Folder 26)
  - John Lindsay Campaigns (Mayor and Congress), 4.
    Thornburgh's interest in John Lindsay was due to "his rising stature as a symbol of moderate Republicanism," ("Evidence" draft, p. 91). Thornburgh had first heard him speak in Pittsburgh at a 1961 campaign rally for Pittsburgher John Tabor, then running for city council. Lindsay at the time was a U.S. Congressman and went on to a surprising victory in the New York mayoralty campaign in 1965. The files here consist of campaign material, correspondence, annotated newspaper and magazine clippings, statements and news releases.
    - Campaign Material for Lindsay's Re-Election Campaigns for Congress, 1962-1964 (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence between Thornburgh and Lindsay, 1963-1965 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings about John Lindsay (annotated), 1964-1967 (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - Campaign Material for Lindsay's Campaign for Mayor of New York, 1965 (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings regarding Lindsay's Campaign for Mayor of New York (annotated), 1965 (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - Lindsay's Statements and Press Releases, 1967-1968 (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - Campaign Material for Lindsay's Re-Election Campaign for Mayor of New York, 1969 (Box 20, Folder 7)
    - Magazine Articles Post Lindsay's Election to Mayor of New York, 1965-1978 (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Rockefeller for President, 5.
    Shortly after Dick Thornburgh's participation in Pennsylvania's Constitutional Convention (see extensive files here in Section 6) the national political scene in 1968 included New York Governor Nelson Rockefeller's campaign for the Republican presidential nomination, contesting former Vice-President Nixon. The Rockefeller forces had recruited Thornburgh as their Western Pennsylvania chairman. These files are organized into the "Presidential Campaign Scene in 1968," "Campaign fact sheets, mailings and handouts" and "Western Pennsylvanians for Rockefeller for President." The material consists of reports, correspondence, campaign handouts, mailings, Rockefeller speeches, news releases, position papers, and annotated notes that together well represent national politics in action at the local level.
    - Presidential Campaign Scene in 1968
      - "Metropolitan Areas and Key Counties in the Presidential Election of 1964," by the Republican National Committee, June, 1965 (Box 20, Folder 9)
      - "Presidential '68," in Congressional Quarterly Weekly Report, September 29, 1967 (Box 20, Folder 10)
      - Correspondence, Notes, and Clippings on 1968 Presidential Campaign (Box 20, Folder 11)
      - Humphrey for President, Campaign Mailings, 1968 (Box 20, Folder 12)
      - Nixon for President, Campaign Mailings, 1966-1968 (Box 20, Folder 13)
      - GOP Truth Squad Information for 1968 Presidential Campaign, October, 1968 (Box 20, Folder 14)
      - McCarthy for President, Campaign Mailings, 1968 (Box 20, Folder 15)
      - Wallace for President, Campaign Mailings, 1968 (Box 20, Folder 16)
    - Campaign Fact Sheets, Mailings and Handouts
      - Fact Sheets and Information on Rockefeller, 1964-1968 (Box 20, Folder 17)
      - Campaign Mailings, 1968 (Box 20, Folder 18)
      - Media and Handouts, 1968 (Box 20, Folder 19)
      - Memoranda, 1968 (Box 20, Folder 20)
      - "News from Rockefeller for President", 1968 (Box 20, Folder 21)
      - Rockefeller's Speeches and Position Papers, 1968 (Box 20, Folder 22)
      - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings, 1968 (Box 20, Folder 23)
    - Western Pennsylvanians for Rockefeller for President
      - Pennsylvanians for Rockefeller News Releases, 1968 (Box 21, Folder 1)
      - Western Pennsylvanians for Rockefeller News Releases, May-August, 1968 (Box 21, Folder 2)
      - Western Pennsylvania for Rockefeller, Correspondence and Notes, 1968 (Box 21, Folder 3)
      - Rockefeller for President Committee, Correspondence, News Releases, and Notes, 1968 (Box 21, Folder 4)
      - Endorsements for Rockefeller, 1968 (Box 21, Folder 5)
      - Anti-Rockefeller Correspondence, 1968 (Box 21, Folder 6)
      - Letter from Rockefeller to Thornburgh, June 11, 1968 (Box 21, Folder 7)
      - Campaign Correspondence, 1967-1968 (Box 21, Folder 8)
      - "The Case for Nelson Rockefeller," by Dick Thornburgh, 1968 (Box 21, Folder 9)
      - Campaign Headquarters Notes, 1968 (Box 21, Folder 10)
      - Campaign Headquarters Staff and Volunteers, 1968 (Box 21, Folder 11)
      - Young Republicans and Pennsylvania Students for Rockefeller, James Seif Correspondence and Notes, 1968 (Box 21, Folder 12)
      - Resumes for Campaign Headquarters Staff, 1968 (Box 21, Folder 13)
      - Campaign Supplies, 1968 (Box 21, Folder 14)